<!--da modificare-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                Lettera sul digiuno A digital edition
                </title>
                <author>
                Chiara d'Assisi
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
                    <name>Chiara Parravicini</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> DHDK Digital Edition <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
                <authority>Chiara Parravicini</authority>                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="it">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>
                        Lettera sul digiuno
                        </title>
                        <author>
                        Chiara d'Assisi
                        </author>
                        <editor>
                        <!--da riguardare-->
                        </editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition> <!--da riguardare--> <date when=""><!--da riguardare--></date>
                        </edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure unit="pages" quantity=""><!--da riguardare--></measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher><!--da riguardare--></publisher>
                        <date when=""><!--da riguardare--></date>   
                        <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>  
                        <availability target=""><!--da riguardare-->
                        </availability>          
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <!--da riguardare--> 
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                Basic encoding, capturing information related to main characters and aiming to interpret the texts through concept-like structures. All hyphenation, punctuation, and variant spelling normalized. No formatting or layout information preserved.
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This letter was selected in order to create this digial edition. The sample was chosen on the basis of the topics touched upon in the text.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <tagsUsage gi="seg" occurs="25">
                    Used to mark segments of text addressed through @ana to a specific interpretation of the segments themselves.
                </tagsUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
                    
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="ChiaradAssisi">
                        <persName>
                            Chiara d'Assisi
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="FrancescodAssisi">
                        <persName>
                            Francesco d'Assisi
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AgnesediBoemia">
                        <persName>
                            Agnese di Boemia
                        </persName> 
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="GesudiNazareth">
                        <persName>
                            Gesù di Nazareth
                        </persName> 
                    </person>   
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <interpGrp resp="#ChiaraParravicini"
    type="structuralunit">
        <interp xml:id="beauty">beauty</interp>
        <interp xml:id="counterstereotype">counterstereotype</interp>
        <interp xml:id="education">education</interp>
        <interp xml:id="gender">gender stereotype</interp>
        <interp xml:id="grace">grace and false grace</interp>
        <interp xml:id="intellect">intellect</interp>
        <interp xml:id="marriage">marriage</interp>
        <interp xml:id="mother">mother</interp>
        <interp xml:id="rights">rights</interp>
        <interp xml:id="society">society</interp>
        <interp xml:id="strength">strength</interp>
        <interp xml:id="weakness">weakness</interp>
            
    </interpGrp>

    <text>
        <h2>Author's Introduction</h2>
        After considering the historic page, and viewing the
        living world with anxious solicitude, the most melan-
        choly emotions of sorrowful indignation have depressed
        my spirits, and I have sighed when obliged to confess
        that either Nature has made a great difference between
        man and man, or that the civilization which has hitherto
        taken place in the world has been very partial. I have
        turned over various books written on the subject of
        education, and patiently observed the conduct of parents
        and the management of <seg xml:id="seg1" ana="#education">schools</seg>; but what has been
        the result? - a profound conviction that the <seg xml:id="seg1.1" ana="#education">neglected
        education</seg> of my fellow-creatures is the grand source of
        the misery I deplore, and that women, in particular, are
        rendered weak and wretched by a variety of concurring
        causes, originating from one hasty conclusion. The con-
        duct and manners of women, in fact, evidently prove
        that their minds are not in a healthy state; for, like the
        flowers which are planted in too rich a soil, strength and
        usefulness are sacrificed to <seg xml:id="seg2" ana="#beauty">beauty</seg>; and the flaunting
        leaves, after having pleased a fastidious eye, fade, disre-
        garded on the stalk, long before the season when they
        ought to have arrived at maturity. One cause of this
        barren blooming I attribute to a <seg xml:id="seg1.2" ana="#education">false system of edu-
        cation</seg>, gathered from the books written on this subject
        by men who, considering females rather as women than
        human creatures, have been more anxious to make them
        alluring mistresses than affectionate wives and <seg xml:id="seg3" ana="#intellect">rational</seg>
        <seg xml:id="seg4" ana="#mother">mothers</seg>; and the <seg xml:id="seg3.1" ana="#intellect">understanding</seg> of the sex has been
        so bubbled by this specious homage, that the civilized
        women of the present century, with a few exceptions,
        are only anxious to inspire love, when they ought to
        cherish a nobler ambition, and by their abilities and
        virtues exact respect.
        In a treatise, therefore, on <seg xml:id="seg5" ana="#rights">female rights</seg> and manners,
        the works which have been particularly written for their
        improvement must not be overlooked, especially when
        it is asserted, in direct terms, that the minds of women
        are enfeebled by <seg xml:id="seg6" ana="#grace">false refinement</seg>; that the books of
        <seg xml:id="seg1.3" ana="#education">instruction</seg>, written by men of genius, have had the same
        tendency as more frivolous productions; and that, in the
        true style of Mahometanism, they are treated as a kind
        of subordinate beings, and not as a part of the human
        species, when improvable reason is allowed to be the
        dignified distinction which raises men above the brute
        creation, and puts a natural sceptre in a feeble hand.
        Yet, because I am a woman, I would not lead my
        readers to suppose that I mean violently to agitate the
        contested question respecting the quality or inferiority
        of the sex; but as the subject lies in my way, and I cannot
        pass it over without subjecting the main tendency of my
        reasoning to misconstruction, I shall stop a moment to
        deliver, in a few words, my opinion. In the government
        of the physical world it is observable <seg xml:id="seg7" ana="#weakness">that the female in
        point of strength is, in general, inferior to the male</seg>. This
        is the law of Nature; and it does not appear to be
        suspended or abrogated in favour of woman. A degree
        of physical superiority cannot, therefore, be denied, and
        it is a noble prerogative! But not content with this natural
        pre-eminence, men endeavour to sink us still lower,
        merely to render us alluring objects for a moment; and
        women, intoxicated by the adoration which men, under
        the influence of their senses, pay them, do not seek to
        obtain a durable interest in their hearts, or to become
        the friends of the fellow-creatures who find amusement
        in their society.
        I am aware of an obvious inference. From every
        quarter have I heard exclamations against <seg xml:id="seg8" ana="#counterstereotype">masculine
        women</seg>, but where are they to be found? If by this
        appellation men mean to inveigh against their ardour in
        hunting, shooting, and gaming, I shall most cordially
        join in the cry; but if it be against the imitation of manly
        virtues, or, more properly speaking, the attainment of
        those talents and virtues, the exercise of which ennobles
        the human character, and which raises females in the
        scale of animal being, when they are comprehensively
        termed mankind, all those who view them with a philo-
        sophic eye must, I should think, wish with me, that <seg xml:id="seg8.1" ana="#counterstereotype">they
        may every day grow more and more masculine</seg>.
        This discussion naturally divides the subject. I shall
        first consider women in the grand light of human crea-
        tures, who, in common with men, are placed on this
        earth to unfold their faculties; and afterwards I shall
        more particularly point out their peculiar designation.
        I wish also to steer clear of an error which many
        respectable writers have fallen into; for the <seg xml:id="seg1.4" ana="#education">instruction</seg>
        which has hitherto been addressed to women, has rather
        been applicable to ladies, if the little indirect advice that
        is scattered through 'Sandford and Merton' be excepted;
        but, addressing my sex in a firmer tone, I pay particular
        attention to <seg xml:id="seg9" ana="#society">those in the middle class</seg>, because they
        appear to be in the most natural state. Perhaps the seeds
        of <seg xml:id="seg6.1" ana="#grace">false refinement</seg>, immorality, and vanity, have ever
        been shed by the great. Weak, artificial beings, raised
        above the common wants and affections of their race, in
        a premature unnatural manner, undermine the very
        foundation of virtue, and spread corruption through the
        whole mass of society! As a class of mankind they have
        the strongest claim to pity; the education of the rich
        tends to render them vain and helpless, and the unfolding
        mind is not strengthened by the practice of those duties
        which dignify the human character. They only live to
        amuse themselves, and by the same law which in Nature
        invariably produces certain effects, they soon only afford
        barren amusement.
        But as I purpose taking a separate view of <seg xml:id="seg9.3" ana="#society">the different
        ranks of society</seg>, and of the moral character of women
        in each, this hint is for the present sufficient; and I have
        only alluded to the subject because it appears to me to
        be the very essence of an introduction to give a cursory
        account of the contents of the work it introduces.
        My own sex, I hope, will excuse me, if 1 treat them like
        <seg xml:id="seg3.2" ana="#intellect">rational creatures</seg>, instead of flattering their <seg xml:id="seg6.2" ana="#grace">fascinating
        graces</seg>, and viewing them as if they were in a state of
        perpetual childhood, <seg xml:id="seg7.1" ana="#weakness">unable to stand alone</seg>. I earnestly
        wish to point out in what true dignity and human happi-
        ness consists. I wish to persuade women to endeavour
        to acquire <seg xml:id="seg10" ana="#strength"><seg xml:id="seg3.3" ana="#intellect">strength, both of mind</seg> and body</seg>, and to
        convince them that the soft; phrases, susceptibility of
        heart, delicacy of sentiment, and refinement of taste, are
        almost synonymous with epithets of <seg xml:id="seg7.2" ana="#weakness">weakness</seg>, and that
        those beings who are only the objects of pity, and that
        kind of love which has been termed its sister, will soon
        become objects of contempt.
        Dismissing, then, those <seg xml:id="seg6.3" ana="#grace">pretty feminine phrases</seg>,
        which the men condescendingly use to soften our slavish
        dependence, and despising that weak elegancy of mind,
        exquisite sensibility, and <seg xml:id="seg6.4" ana="#grace">sweet docility of manners</seg>, sup-
        posed to be the sexual characteristics of the <seg xml:id="seg7.3" ana="#weakness">weaker
        vessel</seg>, I wish to show that elegance is inferior to virtue,
        that the first object of laudable ambition is to obtain a
        character as a human being, regardless of the distinction
        of sex, and that secondary views should be brought to
        this simple touchstone.
        This is a rough sketch of my plan; and should I express
        my conviction with the energetic emotions that I feel
        whenever I think of the subject, the dictates of experience
        and reflection will be felt by some of my readers. Ani-
        mated by this important object, I shall disdain to cull my
        phrases or polish my style. I aim at being useful, and
        sincerity will render me unaffected; for wishing rather
        to persuade by the force of my arguments than dazzle
        by the elegance of my language, I shall not waste my
        time in rounding periods, or in fabricating the turgid
        bombast of artificial feelings, which, coming from the
        head, never reach the heart. I shall be employed about
        things, not words! and, anxious to render my sex <seg xml:id="seg6.5" ana="#grace">more
        respectable members of society</seg>, I shall try to avoid that
        flowery diction which has slided from essays into novels,
        and from novels into familiar letters and conversations.
        These pretty superlatives, dropping glibly from the
        tongue, vitiate the taste, and create a kind of sickly deli-
        cacy that turns away from simple unadorned truth; and
        a deluge of false sentiments and overstretched feelings,
        stifling the natural emotions of the heart, render the
        domestic pleasures insipid, that ought to sweeten the
        exercise of those severe duties, which educate a rational
        and immortal being for a nobler field of action.
        The <seg xml:id="seg1.5" ana="#education">education of women</seg> has of late been more
        attended to than formerly; yet they are still reckoned a
        frivolous sex, and ridiculed or pitied by the writers who
        endeavour by satire or instruction to improve them. It
        is acknowledged that they spend many of the first years of
        their lives in acquiring a smattering of accomplishments;
        meanwhile <seg xml:id="seg10.1" ana="#strength">strength of body</seg> and <seg xml:id="seg3.4" ana="#intellect">mind</seg> are sacrificed to
        libertine notions of <seg xml:id="seg2.1" ana="#beauty">beauty</seg>, to the desire of establishing
        themselves - the only way women can rise in the world
        - by <seg xml:id="seg12" ana="#marriage">marriage</seg>. And this desire making mere animals of
        them, when they marry they act as such children may
        be expected to act - they dress, they paint, and nickname
        God's creatures. Surely these <seg xml:id="seg7.4" ana="#weakness">weak beings</seg> are only fit
        for a seraglio! Can they be expected to govern a family
        with <seg xml:id="seg3.5" ana="#intellect">judgement</seg>, or take care of the poor babes whom
        they bring into the world?
        If, then, it can be fairly deduced from the present
        conduct of the sex, from the prevalent fondness for
        pleasure which takes place of ambition and those nobler
        passions that open and enlarge the soul, that the instruc-
        tion which women have hitherto received has only
        tended, with the constitution of <seg xml:id="seg9.2" ana="#society">civil society</seg>, to render
        them insignificant objects of desire - mere <seg xml:id="seg4.1" ana="#mother">propagators</seg>
        of fools! - if it can be proved that in aiming to accomplish
        them, <seg xml:id="seg1.6" ana="#education">without cultivating their understandings</seg>, they are
        taken out of their sphere of duties, and made ridiculous
        and useless when <seg xml:id="seg2.2" ana="#beauty">the short-lived bloom of beauty</seg> is
        over, I presume that rational men will excuse me for
        endeavouring to persuade them to <seg xml:id="seg8.2" ana="#counterstereotype">become more mascu-
        line</seg> and respectable.
        Indeed the word masculine is only a bugbear; there is
        little reason to fear that women will acquire <seg xml:id="seg10.2" ana="#strength">too much
        courage or fortitude</seg>, for their <seg xml:id="seg7.5" ana="#weakness">apparent inferiority with
        respect to bodily strength</seg> must render them in some
        degree dependent on men in the various relations of life; but why should it be increased 
        by <seg xml:id="seg11" ana="#gender">prejudices that give a
        sex to virtue</seg>, and confound simple truths with sensual reveries?
        Women are, in fact, so much degraded by <seg xml:id="seg11.1" ana="#gender">mistaken
        notions of female excellence</seg>, that I do not mean to add
        a paradox when I assert that this <seg xml:id="seg7.6" ana="#weakness">artificial weakness</seg>
        produces a propensity to tyrannize, and gives birth to
        cunning, the natural opponent of strength, which leads
        them to play off those contemptible infantine airs that
        undermine esteem even whilst they excite desire. Let
        men become more chaste and modest, and <seg xml:id="seg3.6" ana="#intellect">if women do
        not grow wiser in the same ratio it will be clear that they
        have weaker understandings</seg>. It seems scarcely necessary
        to say that I now speak of the sex in general. Many indi-
        viduals have more sense than their male relatives; and, as
        nothing preponderates where there is a constant struggle
        for an equilibrium without it has naturally more gravity,
        some women govern their husbands without degrading
        themselves, because intellect will always govern.


    </text>
</TEI>